Guide to the David Grant Noble Photographs of Southwestern Cultural Landscapes
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
David Grant Noble Photographs of Southwestern Cultural Landscapes
1971-2002
WA Photos Folio 142
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.1
4 boxes
Noble, David Grant
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David Grant Noble on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2009-2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
David Grant Noble (born 1939)
David Grant Noble (Yale 1961) was born and raised in rural Massachusetts. He majored in French at Yale University, and began photographing seriously in 1962 while serving in army counterintelligence in Vietnam. During the 1960s, he lived in New York City and wrote articles and photographed for the weekly newspaper, Manhattan East. In 1971, Noble moved to New Mexico. Initially, he worked as the record photographer for archaeological excavations by the School of American Research at Arroyo Hondo Pueblo near Santa Fe; he continued to work for the school until 1989. In 2003, Noble received the Victor Stoner Award from the Arizona Archaeological and Historical Society in recognition of his "outstanding efforts to bring historical and archaeological awareness of the Southwest to the general public." In 2011, he received the Emil Haury Award from the Western National Parks Association for "outstanding contributions in scientific research or other activities that advance the understanding and interpretation of the natural and cultural resources of western national parks."
Scope and Contents
Photographs created by David Grant Noble documenting cultural landscapes in the American Southwest, 1971-2002. The images document petroglyphs, structures, cliff dwellings, and other reminders of the ancestors of Southwestern Native American people and cultures. Many images appear in his book, In the Places of the Spirits (Santa Fe, New Mexico: School for Advanced Research Press, 2010).
Photographs of structures in Arizona include White House Ruin and Antelope House Ruin at Canyon de Chelly; Spanish Cavalcade and Mummy Cave at Canyon del Muerto; and Kiet Siel and Betatakin cliff dwellings at Navajo National Monument, as well as sites at Petrified Forest National Park and Wupatki National Monument.
Photographs of structures in Colorado include Spruce Tree House in Mesa Verde. There are also several images of sites at Hovenweep National Monument, which straddles the border between southwestern Colorado and southeastern Utah, including House Ruin and Holly Ruin.
Photographs of structures in New Mexico include Pueblo Bonito in Chaco Canyon; Kin Ya-a at Crownpoint; and Tyonyi Pueblo and Cavates at Frijoles Canyon; as well as sites at Bandelier National Monument and Gila Cliff Dwellings National Monument.
Photographs of structures in Utah include Monarch Cave and Moon House at Cedar Mesa and a cliff dwelling along the San Juan River.
There is also a photograph of a structure at the Casas Grandes Site in Chihuahua, Mexico.
Photographs of petroglyphs in Arizona include works in Canyon del Muerto.
Photographs of petroglyphs in Colorado include works at Mancos Valley and San Luis Valley.
Photographs of petroglyphs in New Mexico include works at Galisto Basin in Santa Fe County, Glorieta, El Guique, Pecos Pueblo Site, Petroglyph National Monument, Pony Hills in Luna County, Three Rivers, and Velarde, as well as near the Santa Fe River.
Photographs of petroglyphs in Utah include works at Bluff, Canyonlands National Park, Dry Fork Canyon in Uintah County, Grand Gulch Primitive Area, and San Rafael Swell, as well as near the San Juan River.
The collection also includes landscape photographs of sites in New Mexico including Bosque del Apache National Wildlife Refuge, Chama Valley, and Llano Estacado. There is also a view of a waterfall in Havasu Canyon (also known as Cataract Creek Canyon) in Arizona.
Arrangement
Arranged by David Grant Noble.
Landscape photography -- Southwest, New; Natural history -- Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Petroglyphs -- Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Pueblos -- Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Sacred space -- Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Arizona -- Pictorial works; Bandelier National Monument (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Bluff (Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Bosque del Apache National Wildlife Refuge (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Canyon de Chelly National Monument (Ariz.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Canyonlands National Park (Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Casas Grandes Site (Mexico) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Cedar Mesa (San Juan County, Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Chaco Canyon (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Chama Valley (Colo. and N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Chelly, Canyon de (Ariz.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Colorado -- Pictorial works; Crownpoint (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Dry Fork Canyon (Uintah County, Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; El Guique (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Frijoles Canyon (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Gila Cliff Dwellings National Monument (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Glorieta (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Grand Gulch Primitive Area (Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Havasu Canyon (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; Horseshoe Canyon (Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Hovenweep National Monument (Utah and Colo.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Llano Estacado -- Pictorial works; Mancos Valley (Colo.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Mesa Verde National Park (Colo.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Muerto, Canyon del (Apache County, Ariz.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Navajo National Monument (Ariz.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; New Mexico -- Pictorial works; Pecos Pueblo Site (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Petroglyph National Monument (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Pony Hills (Luna County, N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Pueblo Bonito Site (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; San Juan River (Colo.-Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; San Luis Valley (Colo. and N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; San Rafael Swell (Utah) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Santa Fe County (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Santa Fe River (New Mexico) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Southwest, New -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Three Rivers (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Utah -- Pictorial works; Velarde (N.M.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Wupatki National Monument (Ariz.) -- Antiquities -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Noble, David Grant
- Photographs, 1971-2002; 80
  Scope and Contents
  Titles of photographs and accompanying descriptions provided by David Grant Noble.
  - Betatakin Ruins, Northwestern Arizona, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Related Materials
    See also: Betakin, Arizona, Box 3, folder 58
    Noble: "Ancestral Pueblo Indians, part of the Kayenta-Anasazi branch, began construction of Betatakin ("Ledge House" in Navajo) in the mid-1200s but lived in the village for less than a decade before moving on. A five-hundred foot-high natural rock amphitheater has protected the site so effectively that some roofs and ceilings remain intact. Richard Wetherill and Byron Cummings, who first recorded this cliff dwelling in 1907, found an abundance of artifacts untouched for centuries. Navajos, who moved into the region after the Pueblos had departed, stayed away from places like Betatakin believing them to be haunted."
  - Jicarilla Apache Pictograph Panel, San Luis Valley, Colorado, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Noble: "After their arrival in the American Southwest from the north, the Jicarilla band of Apaches claimed areas of what is now southern Colorado and northern New Mexico as their home territory. This pictograph panel appears on a rock surface in southern Colorado's San Luis Valley. Painted in reddish pigments, it depicts human and animal figures as well as wheel-like and abstract designs."
  - White House and Rock Art Figures, Canyon de Chelly, Arizona, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Noble: "This close-up view of White House in Canyon de Chelly shows its fine masonry. Some archaeologists believe the building to be an outlying Chacoan great house. The pictographs on the cliff are characteristically Puebloan in style and probably date to the late Pueblo II or early Pueblo III period. Beneath the cliff dwelling are the remains of a larger now-collapsed multistory pueblo. Setting ladders on its top-story roof, White House residents could access the ledge."
  - Pictographs and Swallow Nests, Mancos River Valley, Colorado, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Noble: "This painting of a woman, along the Mancos River, is of relatively recent origin. Some believe it to be a portrait of the wife of Chief Jack House, the last traditional chief of the Ute Mountain Ute Apaches. Chief House, who died in 1971, lived in a cabin located close by. The negative handprints probably date to a much earlier Pueblo time period. Above the pictographs the mud nests of cliff swallows are visible."
  - Detail of the "Ghost Panel," Horseshoe Canyon, Utah, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Noble: "Archaic-period Indians painted these near life-size ghostlike figures more than 1500 years ago on the west side of the Colorado River in southeastern Utah. The panel, which remains in remarkably good condition after centuries of exposure to the elements, is an outstanding example of ancient shamanic art."
  - Pueblo Bonito Doorways, Chaco Canyon, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    See also: Spruce Tree House in Snowstorm, Mesa Verde, Colorado, Box 3, folder 60
    Noble: "Many people think Pueblo Bonito represents the finest example of pre-Columbian American architecture. Its thick masonry walls, some reaching four and five stories in height, were faced with hand-hewn pieces of sandstone. Its ancestral Pueblo builders started construction on the structure around 850 CE, adding to it incrementally for three centuries. Most experts today think Pueblo Bonito had relatively few residents of an elite class but was visited periodically by pilgrims to attend religious ceremonies."
  - Spruce Tree House in Snowstorm, Mesa Verde, Colorado, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Noble: "In the thirteenth century, ancestral Pueblo people built hundreds of granaries, houses, and even entire villages in the shelter of rock alcoves and clefts in the canyon cliffs of Mesa Verde. Spruce Tree House, one of the largest with 114 rooms and eight kivas is thought to have housed up to a hundred people. Its residents obtained their water from a spring up the canyon. Trails up the west and east sides provided access to the mesa top."
  - Riders Chasing a Deer, Canyon del Muerto, Arizona, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Noble: "Navajo rock art has a distinctly different style and character from that of the prehistoric Pueblo Indians. In Canyon de Chelly and Canyon del Muerto one can find numerous finely executed panels made in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries which depict narrative scenes and show horses and riders in motion. Note the delicately drawn limbs, abstracted heads and necks, and fluid bodies of the animals."
  - White House and Sheep, Canyon de Chelly, Arizona, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Noble: "Navajo farmers and sheepherders began living in and around Canyon de Chelly after its Pueblo inhabitants had left. In January, 1864, US troops led by Kit Carson captured the Canyon de Chelly Navajos and incarcerated them at Fort Sumner until 1865, when the survivors returned. Today, many still make their homes in the canyon and along its rims, raising sheep, serving as guides, and commuting to jobs in nearby Chinle."
  - House Ruin, Hovenweep Area, Colorado, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Noble: "This small structure, built and used in the 1200s, is part of the Holly site group in Hovenweep National Monument. The Puebloan people who built it belonged to the Mesa Verdean or Northern San Juan culture. An extended late thirteenth century drought caused conflicts and eventually emigration from the region."
  - Archaic Pictographs, Horseshoe Canyon, Utah and Archaic Figures, The Maze, Utah, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    See also: Ute Petroglyph of a Horse, Bluff, Utah, Box 3, folder 48
    See also: Archaic Figures, the Maze, Canyonlands, Utah, Box 4, folder 74
    Noble: "Shamanic art flourished in the Archaic Period in the American Southwest. The Canyonlands area of southeastern Utah contains many examples pictographs of anthropomorphic figures in the Barrier Canyon Style which have a ghostlike or otherworldly appearance and appear to float between rock and air, between one world and another. They may have small heads, vestigial or no limbs, and torsos containing designs and animal figures. They can be life-size or smaller in scale and sometimes are accompanied by animal or bird figures, perhaps showing the shaman's spirit leaving his human body."
  - Pecos Pueblo Mounds in Winter, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Noble: "Pecos Pueblo, a major population center and trading center between around 1450 and 1700, holds a commanding view of the Pecos River valley east of Santa Fe. Excavations of the site by Alfred V. Kidder in the 1920s are considered a landmark in the history of American archaeology. In 1838, the last surviving Pecos Indians left and went to live with their fellow Tiwa speakers in Jemez Pueblo."
  - Petroglyphs and Clouds, Santa Fe River Canyon, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Noble: "This small compact panel of figures pecked on a basalt boulder in the lower Santa Fe River Canyon contains a spiral, two anthropomorphic figures, masks, and abstract designs: all common Rio Grande Style imagery. Pueblo Indians lived in the vicinity between the early fourteenth and late seventeenth centuries."
  - Fremont Petroglyphs, Dry Fork Canyon, Utah, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Noble: "The Fremont Culture is poorly understood by the archaeological community and even defining it has proven problematical. These anthropomorphic figures, thought to date to between 650 and 900 CE, are in the Classic Vernal Style found in northeastern Utah. The figures wear elaborate headgear and one appears to be holding a severed head."
  - Sixteen-Room House, Along the San Juan River, Utah, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Noble: "This single-story cliff dwelling, situated in a high shallow cliff alcove along the San Juan River, is unusual both in that it faces north and was never completed. Had its ancestral Pueblo builders finished its construction, they probably would have lived in it only during the warm season or just used it for year-round food storage."
  - Petroglyph Panel, Comanche Gap, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Noble: "Also in the Galisteo Basin, this dense concentration of petroglyphs includes horned serpents, anthropomorphs, birds, animals, and snakes along with a star (with headdress) and a mask. Contemporary interpretations of the meaning and significance of such a panel are speculative and the Puebloan descendants of the people who made the glyphs tend to keep their traditional knowledge private."
  - Cliff Dwelling, Gila Cliffs, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Noble: "Cliff dwellings, which are so closely associated with Four Corners Puebloan culture, are only rarely found in Mogollon country, which lies far to the south. This example along the West Fork of the Gila River in southern New Mexico testifies to the widespread influence of the Puebloan or Anasazi culture. Since it dates to the late 1200s, a time when the Four Comers region was being depopulated, it may have been built by migrants. Early American miners and settlers stripped this site and others nearby of their artifacts."
  - Anthropomorphic Figures, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Noble: "After around 1300 CE and until the early historic period, the Galisteo Basin was dotted with pueblos, some containing multiple room blocks and plazas. The valley also has extensive collections of rock art. These petroglyph figures appear behind a Tanoan Pueblo village whose inhabitants joined the Pueblo Revolt of 1680 and occupied Santa Fe until the Spanish Reconquest when they went to live among the Hopis on First Mesa, Arizona."
  - Bighorn Sheep, Three Rivers, New Mexico, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    See also: Stylized Lion Petroglyph. Three Rivers, New Mexico, Box 4, folder 67
    Noble: "This depiction of a desert bighorn sheep impaled by spears is among thousands of petroglyphs pecked on boulders along a ridge near the western base of the Sacramento Mountains in south-central New Mexico. They were made by Jornada Mogollon people, closely related to the Mimbres, and are dated to between around 1050 and 1400 CE. Bighorn sheep were a food source and the image may have been made as part of a hunting-magic ritual."
  - A Cliff House, Cedar Mesa, Utah, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    See also: Cliff Dwelling 1, Cedar Mesa, Utah, Box 3, folder 50
    Noble: "This cliff dwelling in southeastern Utah has been so well sheltered and little visited over the centuries that its mud-and-stone walls, doorways, wood ceilings, and even paintings on plaster remain in fine condition. Cedar Mesa, which is transected by a series of canyons draining into the San Juan River, was a major area of habitation by Native Americans in the prehistoric period. It was depopulated in the late thirteenth century."
  - Antelope House, Canyon de Chelly, Arizona, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Noble: "Antelope House is an ancestral Pueblo village site located on the bank of Chinle Wash in northeastern Arizona and dating from about 1100 to 1300. Archaeological excavations in the 1920s and 1970s revealed that this once was a multistory pueblo with a resident population of between fifty and ninety people. Part of a Navajo farmer's field can be seen in the lower right portion of the photograph."
  - Negative Handprints, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Noble: "Handprints are found ubiquitously in Southwestern rock art; indeed, in rock art throughout the world. These examples appear in a large alcove near the cliff dwelling known as Sixteen-Room House, along the San Juan River in southeastern Utah. They were made by placing a hand against the rock and blowing iron-oxide pigment against it to create a negative image."
  - The Maze, Canyonlands, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Noble: "Unusual landmarks and outstanding topographic features inspire stories and legends, which lend sacred character to a landscape. These four pinnacles in the Maze district of Canyonlands jut up in a remote, arid, seemingly uninhabitable region of southeastern Utah. However, in prehistoric times hunter-gatherers knew the area well and left signs of their presence in the form of elaborate rock art. Later, ancestral Pueblo pioneers tried farming certain open spaces within the network of canyons."
  - Footprint Trail Pony Hill Site, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    See also: Tinaja, Pony Hill Site, New Mexico, Box 4, folder 66
    Noble: "A concentration of petroglyphs around natural pools at Pony Hills in southwestern New Mexico includes this unusual series of pecked footprints. The images were created by people of the Mimbres culture, a branch of the Mogollon, which thrived between around 1000 and 1150. Mimbres artisans are especially known for their beautifully painted pottery."
  - Running Figure, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Noble: "This figure of a running man holding a stick is unusual in Rio Grande iconography. Not shown in the photograph are a turkey and a second running figure, possibly representing a hunting scene. It is part of a dense concentration of rock art near the ruins of San Cristobal Pueblo, a large village occupied by Tanoan Pueblo people prior to the 1680 Pueblo Revolt, when warriors from San Cristobal played a key role in defeating the Spanish colonists and occupying Santa Fe."
  - Awanyu, the Horned Serpent, Galisteo Basin, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Noble: "The horned serpent or Awanyu is a deity or mythological being in certain Pueblo traditions. This detail of Awanyu, part of a larger petroglyph panel, shows in close-up the way it often appears in the Galisteo Basin, with an animal-like face, open mouth, and graceful forward-bending horn. Scholars think the horned serpent may be a northern expression of Quetzalcoatl, the Plumed Serpent, who was an important Mesoamerican deity."
  - Archaic Pictographs, San Rafael Swell, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Noble: "This panel of elongated, reddish-painted anthropomorphic figures are part of the Buckhorn Wash Site located in a rugged area of eastern Utah known as the San Rafael Swell. The precise date of this and other nearby rock art sites has been hard to determine, but scholars estimate that they are between 1,500 and 3,000 years old. Fremont people inhabited the region after around 500 CE. The Buckhorn Wash pictographs closely resemble Archaic-period imagery found not far to the south in Barrier (Horseshoe) Canyon. In historic times, passers-by heavily vandalized this artwork; fortunately, in the 1990s local citizens raised funds to have it professionally restored."
  - Spiral Petroglyph, Velarde, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Noble: "Spirals frequently occur in rock art. In the Southwest, some Native Americans see them as symbolic of water, others as representing migrations that their ancestors made after emerging into this world from a previous, world beneath. In the latter interpretation, the spirals represent the wanderings of the people as they searched for a permanent home in their new world."
  - Kiva, Pecos Pueblo, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Noble: "Inhabited between circa 1200 and 1838 by Towa-speaking Pueblo Indians, Pecos Pueblo thrived as a trade center between the southern Great Plains and the Rio Grande Valley. This kiva and much of the pueblo ruins were excavated between 1915 and 1927 by the noted archaeologist Alfred Vincent Kidder, and later restored."
  - Kin Ya-a, Crownpoint, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Noble: "The ruins of Kin Ya-a (which translates to "standing up house" in Navajo), an outlying Chacoan great house, lie in the southern San Juan Basin south of Chaco Canyon and near the present-day Navajo town of Crownpoint. Great houses such as Kin Ya-a bear testimony to the far-ranging influence of Chaco from around 1050 CE to the mid-12th century. The great house contained 26 ground-floor rooms as well as second and third stories and three enclosed kivas. It is especially noted for its tall tower kiva, a portion of which still stands."
  - Fremont Petroglyphs, Dry Fork Canyon, Utah, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Noble: "These impressive broad-shouldered and elaborately decorated anthropomorphic figures are typical of the Classic Vernal Style of Fremont rock art. They are believed to represent shamans or possibly the supernatural beings envisioned by shamans during trance states. Fremont people lived in the Dry Fork Canyon region after around 650 CE. Archaeologists have found clay figurines in caves that are similar in style to these petroglyphs."
  - Tyuonyi Pueblo and Cavates, Frijoles Canyon, New Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)